<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-02-21T12:17:13+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Dr. Will Barker (威廉 巴克尔) | theoretical physics, cosmology</title><subtitle>This site is for theoretical, high-energy and gravitational physics and cosmology (broadly defined). More specific topics might include differential geometry, geometric algebra, gauge theories of gravity. Blog-Mu-Nu is a blog which reviews interesting arXiv preprints from [gr-qc], [hep-th] and [astro-ph].</subtitle><author><name>Dr. Will E. V. Barker</name></author><entry><title type="html">arXiv Jan 4th-8th 2020</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/09/post-1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="arXiv Jan 4th-8th 2020" /><published>2021-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/09/post-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/09/post-1.html">&lt;head&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://polyfill.io/v3/polyfill.min.js?features=es6&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script id=&quot;MathJax-script&quot; async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/mathjax@3/es5/tex-mml-chtml.js&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2012.14984&quot;&gt;2012.14984&lt;/a&gt; xPPN: An implementation of the parametrized post-Newtonian formalism using xAct for Mathematica&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Many in the physics community are familiar with the &lt;tt&gt;xAct&lt;/tt&gt; tensor manipulation suite for &lt;tt&gt;Mathematica&lt;/tt&gt;, and those who aren't probably should be. In recent years, &lt;tt&gt;xAct&lt;/tt&gt; has consolidated its place as the go-to computer algebra tool in gravitational theory, outperforming various predecessors with its powerful 'canonicalise' function, and attracting a flurry of applied package development. Some of these packages float and others sink: I'm curious to see how Manuel Hohmann's new &lt;tt&gt;xPPN&lt;/tt&gt; package will fare.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Most modifications to Einstein's theory can be cast in the parametrized post-Newtonian (PPN) formalism. PPN allows the theory to be compared, as a ten-parameter modification of the Newtonian theory, against the gold standard set by GR. The implementation of PPN is usually extremely complicated, and varies substantially from theory to theory. Thus xPPN, a general implementation of the PPN formalism, is potentially very exciting.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the heart of the implementation seems to be the definition of two bespoke manifolds for the \(3+1\) decomposition. Assuming that the covariant theory lives in some sense on \(M_4\), a spacelike foliation \(S_3\) and timelike threading \(T_1\) are introduced as separate &lt;tt&gt;xTensor&lt;/tt&gt; manifolds, where \(M_4\cong T_1\times S_3\). This cuts right through the pre-existing notion of ADM decomposition in &lt;tt&gt;xAct&lt;/tt&gt;, which I've wrestled with recently in the context of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2101.02645&quot;&gt;Hamiltonian analysis&lt;/a&gt;. In the end, I kept a single Minkowski manifold \(M_4\), and defined a set of projections accompanied by very many rules. This is not ideal, but the relevant parts of &lt;tt&gt;xAct&lt;/tt&gt; (such as &lt;tt&gt;xCoba&lt;/tt&gt;) have quite patchy documentation, which makes life less than easy! I won't go into the guts of the higher functions of the package, but suffice to say the post-Newtonian potentials are all defined, along with certain 'utility functions' which facilitate the human-assisted expansion. A nice walk-through is provided for a simple Brans-Dicke-like theory, but since I've not tried it out, I can't offer further comment.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My main concern is the 'theory-scope' of the package. This is of course the hardest part to implement, since you can never tell quite in what terms the next theory will be cast. The Brans-Dicke theory obviously inherits much of the machinery of GR, but with an extra scalar \(\psi\) - I expect e.g. the variations on mimetic gravity could be similarly tackled. This scalar naturally has to be defined when using the package, and presumably one may extend to higher-spin fields also. Accordingly I've already recommended &lt;tt&gt;xPPN&lt;/tt&gt; to a colleague who is &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2007.00082&quot;&gt;working on the new relativistic completion of MOND&lt;/a&gt;.
However, it is often interesting to build theories out of a gauge-covariant derivative. Accordingly, the &lt;tt&gt;xPPN&lt;/tt&gt; package defines three connections: Levi-Civita, teleparallel and symmetric-teleparallel. I'm very happy about the last of these, which follows on from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1903.06830&quot;&gt;non-metricity theories&lt;/a&gt; of Jiménez, Heisenberg and Koivisto, and is something I'd like to work on at some point. However, in the short term I'm interested in a free connection, in the context of torsion theories. This is likely workable in the &lt;tt&gt;xPPN&lt;/tt&gt; setup, but might take some &lt;tt&gt;xAct&lt;/tt&gt;-jitsu. Again, I'd have to try.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Overall, this paper introduces software rather than physics, and is structured accordingly. Nonetheless, I am happy to have come across &lt;tt&gt;xPPN&lt;/tt&gt;, and am looking forward to trying it out in the near future.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dr. Will E. V. Barker</name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New arXiv review blog coming soon!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/22/testpost.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New arXiv review blog coming soon!" /><published>2020-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/22/testpost</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/22/testpost.html">&lt;head&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://polyfill.io/v3/polyfill.min.js?features=es6&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script id=&quot;MathJax-script&quot; async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/mathjax@3/es5/tex-mml-chtml.js&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm setting up Blo\(g_{\mu\nu}\) to further hone my skills as a peer-review referee, and to draw well-deserved attention to new preprints that I find interesting. The idea is to write a short review of at least one preprint per week, likely drawn from the &lt;tt&gt;[gr-qc]&lt;/tt&gt;, &lt;tt&gt;[astro-ph]&lt;/tt&gt; or &lt;tt&gt;[hep-th]&lt;/tt&gt; arXiv.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This will likely start in the new year, as I still need to figure out comments on &lt;tt&gt;disqus&lt;/tt&gt;, and how to handle arXiv trackbacks and &lt;tt&gt;RSS&lt;/tt&gt; so that the authors are properly credited.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The idea for Blo\(g_{\mu\nu}\) is unashamedly stolen from Dr. Sunny Vagnozzi's &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sunnyvagnozzi.com/blog&quot;&gt;His Dark CMBlog&lt;/a&gt;. Sunny's &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sunnyvagnozzi.com/&quot;&gt;entire website&lt;/a&gt; is absolutely fantastic, and you should explore it before reading any more of my posts.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dr. Will E. V. Barker</name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>